now that we have discussed the different scheduling
strategies
we have for batch and interactive systems
we can go back
for a moment at the differences between
user-level threads
and kernel-level threads and how they are
related to scheduling
and hopefully now
this should be clear
so we said last time in the previous lecture
that we have
user-level threads and
kernel-level threads
if we use user-level threads then a set of
threads are managed
in the user space but they are all linked
together with
the same kernel thread
so from the perspective of the operating system
the kernel
is picking a process
it could be process A or Process B within
the process
then there can be several user-level threads
and these are
scheduled in user space by the process itself
on the other end if we have kernel-level threads
then the
kernel is actually picking a thread of a specific
process
so it can run thread 1 here then it
can go to
thread 2 here and then you can go back thread
3 here
so these three threads can belong to different
processes
while here you would probably change between thread
1 2 and 3
while the operating system is just running
this process
as we said if you use user-level threads and
one of them
for example issues a request through a
system call to
the operating system the entire process will
go into waiting
so all the threads not just the one that is
asking for some
I/O will stop executing
because of
a blocking call
this does not happen with kernel threads
if we look at the pros and cons so you see
that now
user-level threads are actually extremely good
when you want
to have fast context switch because actually
you can change
the thread that is executing with no real
context switch
you don't need to involve the operating system
to do the
context switch
so you save a lot of time the time it takes
to go from one
quantum of execution to another one and change
the thread
it's basically nothing because everything
happens inside
the process without involving the operating
system
and you can define your own scheduler
so if you don't like the scheduler that we
have in your operating
system to run a set of processes that are CPU-bound
you can
use user-level threads and then write your
own scheduler
with your own policy to run your processes
but the negative side as we said is that if
one thread
blocks because of input output the entire process
blocks so all
the user thread
if you look at kernel level or if you use
kernel-level threads
then it will cost more to do the context switch
so you pay
an overhead
but you can have threads of a multi-threaded
process that
are still executing even if some of them are
into some input
output and they need to wait before they get
access to the
CPU